Guide to the C. John Knoebel papers, 1977-2005.
Knoebel, C. John papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
C. John Knoebel papers, 1967-2011.
7810
Knoebel, C. John.
4.5 Cubic Feet.
Audio recordings, memorabilia, printed materials, publications, research materials, computer media.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Documents, photographs, audiotapes, videos, T-shirts, and magazines documenting C. John Knoebel's work for the Advocate and Triangle Marketing Services, as well as his political activities. Includes interviews with David Goodstein, Phil Andros, and Tom of Finland; surveys and marketing research; gay merchandise catalogs from the 1990s and early 2000s; recordings of radio advertisements for the Advocate; and special issues of the Advocate and other LGBT magazines.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
For over 45 years, Knoebel made significant contributions to LGBT history, first as a pioneer gay activist in New York City from 1969 to 1976 and then during his 33-year career as a senior executive with the publishers of the national gay and lesbian newsmagazine, The Advocate, OUT, and other LGBT magazines from 1979 to 2012.
Born in Waukesha, Wisconsin in October 1947, Knoebel attended the University of Wisconsin/Madison when that campus was a nationally-recognized hotbed of anti-Vietnam war protests. After graduating in June 1969, he moved to New York City to attend graduate school in comparative literature at New York University.
As a young gay man in New York during the politically charged post-Stonewall era, Knoebel quickly became an early member of New York’s pioneering Gay Liberation Front. From November 1969 onwards, Knoebel participated in many GLF protest demonstrations as well as the first Gay Pride March in June 1970. As a member of the GLF 95th Street Gay Men’s Living Collective from June 1970 through January 1971, Knoebel worked with this close-knit housing commune on many GLF projects, helped form numerous gay men’s consciousness-raising groups and spoke at colleges and other venues with the GLF speaker’s bureau. The collective also helped to organize the August 1970 Times Square demonstration that ended with several days of riots in the Village, participated in the week-long protest occupation of NYU’s Weinstein Hall, and helped to establish GLF’s first community center on West 3rd Street.
Along with many other GLF groups from around the county, the 95th Street Collective also attended both sessions of the 1970 Black Panther’s Revolutionary People’s Constitutional Conventions in Philadelphia and Washington, D.C. Knoebel was one of three GLF members who met with Huey Newton following the release of his important essay, “A Letter to Revolutionary Brothers and Sister about the Women’s Liberation and Gay Liberation Movements,” which is considered the first pro-gay, pro-woman proclamation to come out of the radical black civil rights movement.
As a member of the cells, “Femmes against Sexism” and “Gay Male Group,” Knoebel advocated a close affinity between gay liberation and radical feminism. He subsequently joined Steven Dansky and Kenneth Pitchford in founding the Effeminists, a group of gay men who opposed sexism, and co-authored the group's influential statement of purpose, “The Effeminist Manifesto” which has been widely reprinted. The group published its own magazine, Double F: a Magazine of Effeminism, from 1972 to 1976 which gave voice to the group’s often controversial politics about gay men in support of feminism.
During this period, Knoebel had worked in magazine circulation and marketing jobs for a succession of small New York publishing companies. Moving to San Francisco in 1978, Knoebel was at work in the city at another publishing job on the day that Harvey Milk was assassinated and he attended numerous marches and protests that followed.
In 1979, Knoebel was hired as marketing director of The Advocate by its high-profile publisher, David Goodstein, and tasked with expanding the magazine’s fledgling 7,000 member subscriber base. Starting from scratch, Knoebel wrote and mailed The Advocate’s first national direct mail campaigns. For many LGBT Americans, their first experience of receiving a piece of gay-oriented direct mail was from ones that Knoebel mailed for The Advocate. Within the next decade, subscribers increased to over 70,000. In his eventual 30+ years with the publishing firm, Knoebel produced and sent out over fifty million pieces of direct mail promoting the firm’s gay magazines, books, mail order catalogs and other products.
In 1984, Knoebel started a new gay men’s erotic-focused magazine line for the company, including Men, Freshmen and Male Pictorial magazines and served as their publisher for several years. These titles proved to be an important profit source for the company and supported the money-losing Advocate during the worst years of the AIDS epidemic. After David Goodstein’s death, Knoebel served as the president and was part-owner of The Advocate from 1987 to 1992.
Following another ownership change, Knoebel returned to New York continuing with The Advocate as VP Consumer Marketing and was instrumental in The Advocate’s purchase of its New York-based rival, OUT magazine. Knoebel also served as president of The Advocate’s subsidiary, Triangle Marketing Services (TMS), a New York-based mailing list management and brokerage firm that worked with a wide range of LGBT business and non-profit organizations in their direct mail efforts and helped raise sizeable money for many clients including major AIDS charities, as well as LGBT arts and political action groups. Knoebel ended his long career with The Advocate in 2012 after 33 years and six-ownership changes.
Knoebel’s writings from the GLF era appeared in GLF’s newspaper, Come Out!, and in early gay liberation anthologies, including “Out of the Closets: Voices of Gay Liberation” edited by Karla Jay and Allen Young. Over the years, Knoebel has given many interviews and spoken on numerous panels concerned with gay history and politics. See: http://stonewallrebels.wordpress.com/2009/07/02/40-years-after-stonewall-part-3-john-knoebel
Post Advocate, Knoebel continued to help document gay history as an editor of Christopher Street Press, an e-Book publishing venture founded in 2011 by Steven Dansky to preserve and re-issue important LGBT historical documents from the early gay liberation movement. Among Christopher Street Press’s first publications were “Hot August Night/1970, The Forgotten LGBT Riot,” and “The Come Out! Reader,” a facsimile edition of all of the issues of GLF’s pioneering newspaper, Come Out!, which Knoebel co-edited.
In 2013, Knoebel and Dansky partnered again to found a new project, OUTSpoken: Oral History from LGBTQ Pioneers. Initially focused on preserving the stories of the pioneers who gave birth to the modern LGBTQ movement in the decade following the 1969 New York City Stonewall Rebellion, OUTSpoken has now collected many dozens of important first-person LGBT oral histories posted on its dedicated website: www.outspoken.org
A life-long choral singer, Knoebel was a member of LGBT choruses in San Francisco, Los Angeles and New York from 1980 through 2012 singing first tenor. He now lives in Palm Springs, California with Ira Helf, his partner since 1977 whom he married in 2013.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
John Knoebel‘s papers contain important writings, documents, business papers, marketing samples, research studies and audio and visual materials reflecting his life-long involvement in LGBT politics and publishing.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Knoebel, C. John.; Andros, Phil.; Goodstein, David B., 1932-; Tom of Finland, 1920-1991.; Triangle Marketing Services.
Titles:
Advocate (Los Angeles, Calif.)
Subjects:
Gay men -- United States; Periodicals -- Publishing -- United States.
Form and Genre Terms:
Audiotapes.; Audiocassettes.; Video recordings.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- The Advocate
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Publishing and Related Materials
    - The Advocate issues, 1967-08-1991-05-07 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Large gaps between issue dates; Includes Vol. 1 No. 1-2; Vol. 2 No. 9-10, 12;Vol. 3 No. 8; Vol. No. 4; Iss. 105, 214, 361, 419, 576
    - Promotion and subscription materials, 1975-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - David B. Goodstein file, 1975-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - National media coverage of The Advocate, 1975-1994 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - National media coverage of The Advocate, 1977-1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - US Post Office periodical rule waiver, 1977-02-11 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Other Advocate staff history, 1978-2008-04 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Includes photographs, articles
    - The Advocate issues, 1979-1980, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Includes Iss. 284, 298-299, 411
    - GayRun'80 flyer, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Europe project correspondence, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - National media coverage of The Advocate, 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - New York subway advertising project, 1981-03-1981-04 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Includes photographs, notes
    - New York Times advertising, 1981-04-1981-05 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Includes correspondence, ads, articles, ad mock-ups
    - Art boards and page reprints, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Founding and early history of The Advocate articles, 1983, 1994-03, 2011-11 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Billboard campaign, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes original concept sketches, photographs, notes regarding model choice
    - Advocate MEN photo, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - The Advocate issue with notes, 1985-09-17 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - The Advocate issues with notes, 1987, 2007 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - The Advocate issues with notes, 1987-09, 1991-1992-06 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - The Advocate sale negotiations, 1992-12-1993-01 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Advocate MEN calendars, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Liberation Publications, Inc. Stock Purchase Agreements Vol. 1-2, 4, 1993-12-22 (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
    - Long Road to Freedom press quotes, 1994-05-1994-09 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - The Advocate's 25th anniversary exhibition, 1994-06-1994-07 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Includes invitation to exhibit reception, visitor comments on exhibit
    - The Advocate purchase of OUT, 1994-07, 1999-09-2000-11 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - MEN 20th anniversary article, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - The Advocate 40th anniversary invitation, 2007-09-18 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Promo item for gay bars, Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Surveys and Market Research
    - Avanti Communications, 1980-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Includes correspondence, articles, questionnaire
    - Characteristics of Readers of The Advocate, 1980-12; Walker and Struman Research, Inc. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Targeting the Homosexual Market: A Viable Option?, 1980-12; Miller, Marc D. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - The Advocate: PRIZM Subscriber Analysis materials, 1987-12-1995-03; Claritas, Inc. (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Includes correspondence, survey results
    - National media coverage of The Advocate, 1990-09-1992-01 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Advocate MEN survey, 1990-12-1995-12 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - The Advocate: A Profile of Subscribers materials, 1993-09-15-1994-11; Simmons Market Research Bureau, Inc. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Memos on marketing, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - The Gay and Lesbian Market, 1995-01; Packaged Facts (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Press clippings, 1995-01-1998-01 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Includes some correspondence
    - Simmons gay market study correspondence, 1996-05-1997-03 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - The Advocate: A Profile of Subscribers materials, 1996-06-1997-01; Mediamark Research Inc. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Press clippings, 2001-01-2003-06 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Includes some correspondence, LGBT Directory of Services and Resources - NY Metropolitan Area
    - Press clippings, 2001-11-2003-06 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Includes correspondence
    - Press clippings, 2001-08 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - The 2000 Census and Same-Sex Households, 2002; Survey and Evaluation Research Laboratory | The Fenway Institute (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Selling Homosexuality to America, 2002; Rondeau, Paul E. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Direct Mail
    - Direct mail samples, 1980-2010 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Direct mail samples, 1980-2010 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Direct mail samples, 1980-2010 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Direct mail samples, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - DM News, 2000-11-06-2005-08 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Library promotion, Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Malibu Sales
    - Malibu Sales - mail order catalogs, 1986-06-1988-02 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Malibu Man catalog, 1989-03-1989-08 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Vaughn Kincey Superman premium video materials, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Gay Travel Guides notes, Undated (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Media and Related Materials
    - Liberation Publications Inc. Videos
      - Liberation Publication Inc. video notes, 1986-2002 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Advocate MEN Live!, 1986; V-10270; Bisonnes, Fred (Prod.) (Box 2)
        Interview with erotic author Phil Andros (Samuel Stewart)
      - Advocate MEN Live! 2, 1987; V-10271; Bisonnes, Fred (Prod.) (Box 2)
        Interview with erotic artist Tom of Finland
      - Advocate MEN Live! 3, 1987; V-10272; Bisonnes, Fred (Prod.) (Box 2)
      - Advocate MEN Live! 4, 1988; V-10273; Bisonnes, Fred (Prod.) (Box 2)
      - Prime Time: Advocate MEN Live! 5, 1988; V-10274; Bisonnes, Fred (Prod.) (Box 2)
      - Big Buddies: Advocate MEN Live! 6, 1989; V-10275; McQueen, Robert (Prod.) (Box 2)
      - Poetry and Motion: Advocate MEN Live! 7, 1990; V-10276; Summers, John (Prod.) (Box 2)
      - FRESHMEN Tryouts, 1994; V-10277-10278; Powers, Derek (Dir.) (Box 2)
      - Freshmen tryouts production, 1994-08-1994-09 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - The Real FRESHMEN World, 1997; V-10279-10280 (Box 2)
      - Shooting Stars: MEN Magazine Live!, 1997; V-10281 (Box 2)
      - FRESHMEN Getaway Weekend, 1998; V-10282 (Box 2)
      - MEN of Your Dreams, 1998; V-10290 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - MEN Magazine Live!, 2002; V-10283 (Box 2)
      - Team Freshmen, Undated; V-10284 (Box 2)
      - SuperMEN, Undated; V-10285; Summers, John (Dir.) (Box 2)
      - Ryan Idol: A Very Personal View, Undated; V-10286; Saxon, Troy (Dir.) (Box 2)
      - Self Massage, Undated; V-10291 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - "It's a Gay Life" Program and Radio Interviews
      - "It's a Gay Life" program and radio interviews notes, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - David Goodstein KGO radio interview, 1977-08-10; tr-16002 (Box 2)
      - It's a Gay Life: Interview with Dr. Newt Dieter, 1978; tr-16003 (Box 2)
      - Peter Frisch Interview KKTT (The Kat) Radio, 1978-03-03; tr-16004 (Box 2)
      - It's a Gay Life: Interview with David Goodstein, 1978-04-09; tr-16005 (Box 2)
      - It's a Gay Life: Interview with M. Paul Simon, 1978-05-30; tr-16006 (Box 2)
      - It's a Gay Life: Interview with Tim Sacora and Estelle Golden, 1978-07-11; tr-16007 (Box 2)
      - It's a Gay Life: Interview with Frank Carr, 1978-07-26; tr-16008 (Box 2)
    - Radio Ads
      - Radio ads notes, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Advocate commercials 4 - 60 second spots, 1979-1980; tr-16011 (Box 2)
      - The Advocate 5 - 30 second radio spots, 1979-1980; tr-16012 (Box 2)
      - The Advocate commercials - master, 1979-1980; tr-16015 (Box 2)
      - 3 - 30's The Advocate commercials, 1979-04-24; tr-16010 (Box 2)
      - The Advocate 5 - 30 second radio spots, 1979-09; tr-16016 (Box 2)
      - The Advocate commercials, 1979-11; tr-16014 (Box 2)
      - AIDS Preventions message, 1987-04; tr-16009 (Box 2)
      - The Advocate 5 - 30 second radio spots, 1980-11; tr-16013 (Box 2)
  - T-shirts
    - The Advocate: touching your lifestyle, 1978-1999; MU-1900 (Box 5)
      Original tagline of The Advocate
    - The Advocate grey tshirt, 1980-1985; MU-1898 (Box 5)
    - The Advocate grey tshirt, 1980-1985; MU-1899 (Box 5)
    - No on 64 victory party tshirt, 1986-11-04; MU-1891 (Box 5)
      Proposition to quarantine HIV positive people
    - The Advocate 20th anniversary tshirt, 1987; MU-1896-1897 (Box 5)
    - March on Washington for Lesbian, Gay and Bi Equal Rights and Liberation tshirt, 1993-04-25; MU-1890 (Box 5)
    - The Advocate/Stonewall Riots 25th anniversary tshirt, 1994-07; MU-1894-1895 (Box 5)
    - The Advocate Melissa Etheridge tshirt, 1999; MU-1892 (Box 5)
    - The Advocate staff tshirt, Undated; MU-1889 (Box 5)
    - Advocate MEN tshirt, Undated; MU-1893 (Box 5)
- Triangle Marketing Services
  - Press contact, 1992, 1999-2001 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Triangle Marketing Services materials, 1995-2004 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Folio Annual Circulation show materials, 1995-10 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    "9 out of 10 people" direct mail package won silver award
  - Old press releases, 1996-2002 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Non-Advocate Videos
  - 1987: A Gay Review, 1996-1997, 2002; V-10287; David, Carl (Dir.) (Box 2)
  - Highlights from the March on Washington, 1988; V-10288; David, Carl (Dir.) (Box 2)
  - Boots, Biceps, and Bulges: The Life and Works of Tom of Finland, 1988; V-10289; Tom of Finland (Box 2)
  - [2] the movie, 2002; DVD-792; Larue, Chi Chi (Box 2)
  - Gay Voices Gay Legends Vol. 2, Undated; V-10292 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Other LGBT Publications
  - Photo sets and order brochures, 1969-1983 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Early form of porn started in the 1950s
  - Stud issue, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Adult bookstore items, 1972-1973, 1977-1980 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - LGBT magazines with notes, 1976, 1979, 1981-1983, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Gay Comix No. 9 autographed by Jerry Mills
  - Photo and video order brochures, 1977-1987 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - LGBT mail order catalogs, 1983, 1988-01-1996-11 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Assorted publications, 1991, 1996-1997, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - LGBT magazines with notes, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Budapest LGBT magazines, 1991-05-1991-07 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Polish MEN magazine, 1991-06 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Shocking Gray catalogs, 1991-09-1995 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Russian LGBT newspaper Tema, 1992-01, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - LGBT magazines with notes, 1995-1997, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - OutClips online catalog, 1995-01 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Tzabaco catalogs, 1995-09-1999-01 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- Assorted files
  - San Francisco Gay Pride March program, 1979-06-24-1991 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - San Francisco Gay Games program, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - GLAAD direct mail, 1990-06 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Defamation, 1990-06; tr-16010 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Narrated by Harvey Fierstein
  - AIDS: Public Attention and Education Needs, 1991; The Roper Organization Inc. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Los Angeles Gay and Lesbian Community Services Center 20th Anniversary Ball program, 1991-10-19 (Box 4, Folder 18)
SEPARATED MATERIAL
Books - cataloged individually in the Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections
Knoebel, John (Ed.). The Advocate Gay Visitors Guide to San Francisco, 1981 1982
Knoebel, John (Ed.). The Advocate Gay Visitors Guide to San Francisco Revised, 1982 1983
Knoebel, John (Ed.). The Advocate Gay Visitors Guide to Los Angeles Revised, 1982 1983
Liberation Publications Inc. The Advocate, 1987, 1991-05, 20006-06
Donelan, Gerard P. Donelan's Back, 1988
Thompson, Mark (Ed.). Long Road to Freedom: The Advocate History of the Gay and Lesbian Movement, 1994-06
50-50 magazine. 50-50 magazine, 1995
Wilde. Wilde Magazine, 1995-05 1995-11
Two Queens, Inc. HX Magazine, 1996-03
SH!IOUT Publications Inc. SH!OUT, 1997-05-01
POZ Publishing LLC. POZ en Espanol, 1997-06 1997-08
MEN Magazine. MEN 15th Anniversary issue, 1999
Gmunder, Bruno. Pure Men: Best of MEN Magazine, 2001
VMAN. VMAN, 2003-09 2004-02
Quintessential Magazine. Quintessential Magazine, 2004-02